# Motivation letter

I hereby apply for the position "Koordinator/in fuer die IT-Vernetzung und Datenmanagement in Biobanken" at the german biobank node.

Dear Dr. Rufenach,

If you are looking for a creative scientist with IT knowledge, someone with a very strong background in Biology, reproducible research and critical thinking, someone who can understand the need of life science researchers, depict how an IT solution can help them perform their tasks efficiently and effectively, as well as either find or create a tool that respond to their needs, we should definitively meet.

I am an experienced neuro-geneticist with a decade of experience in complex behavioural data production and analysis in fundamental research, a field where one learns quickly that data quality and experiment speed are correlated positively. I am a strong advocate for open FAIR data. More recently, I accumulated experience in the production and implementation of new data analysis standards in fundamental and preclinical research, mainly using R, Rmarkdown and Rshiny. I was also very interested in ontologies and semantic web solutions, while I did not had the possibility to participate in this effort directly, yet. In the last 2 years, I have been working with preclinical researchers, whose results I learned to critic fairly but systematically.

Independently, I have been running Drososhare GmbH and its IT solution development. Drososhare is a web-platform aiming at facilitating peer to peer transactions of GMOs in the life sciences. During the last four years, I learned the difficulties in communicating one's wish to IT developers and how to be more effective at it. I got involved and interested in the science and Berlin startup communities, learning about agile development, business models and specificities of the science market.

I am not so familiar with biobanks, since I used living animals in my research. But from what I have read, the problems in material identifications looks very similar, independently on the nature of the material (antibody, living animals, cell lines or tissue samples), and I would love to hear more about your strategy to minimise/solve these issues. I am one of the few who have both a very strong background in life science research (>10 years, 7 first-authored paper, 1 last-authored paper to come), a decent background in creating IT solutions to help the scientific process and experience in team and project management (I could put the concepts learned in the "Moderation & management" course during my time directing the animal outcome core facility). I am also a quick learner, stress resistant and I like to work in a good atmosphere. My current contract is a 50% position at the HU, it ends in February 2018.

I am looking forward to meet you in person, please reach to me for additional information.

Dr. Julien Colomb

Referees:

Prof. York Winter, york.winter@charite.de

## Curriculum Vitae

Julien COLOMB, PhD in Biology Schillerpromenade 4 12049 Berlin julien.colomb@fu-berlin.de

https://github.com/jcolomb

http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520

Birth: 9 April 1979 in Sion (CH) Married, two children

**Swiss** 



### Summary

After 12 years spent on fundamental research (neuro-genetics) in which I gathered skills in experimental design, team leading and student teaching, I got most interested in open science and research reproducibility as well as the digital tools helping scientists to achieve it. I would like to apply these novel knowledge while doing research and mentoring students.

### Research activities

2017 - present	Postdoctoral fellow, HU (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2015 - 2016	Analysing mulitdimensional dataset: the homecagescan case. Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charité ( <b>Berlin</b> , Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2014 - 2015	Animal core facility director and project manager. Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charite ( <b>Berlin</b> , Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2009 -2013	working on Phenobase. Postdoctoral fellow, FU ( <b>Berlin</b> , Germany), by Prof. B. Brembs
2007-2008	working on "the what and where of operant learning in <i>Drosophila</i> ". Postdoctoral fellow, ESPCI ( <b>Paris</b> , France), by Dr. T. Preat
	working on "appetitive learning in <i>Drosophila</i> ".

#### Commercial activities

2016-present Freelance scientist,

Animal core facility (Charité): organisation lead, data analysis in R, Phenobase

(Exist, HU): literature curation.

2012-present Founder and CEO of Drososhare GmbH (Berlin, Germany), facilitating fruit fly

transactions between scientists

#### Education

2016	FELASA B. HU Berlin
2013	Moderation & management (Continuing Education), FU Berlin/Artop.
2006	PhD in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg, Switzerland).

PhD dissertation: "The chemosensory system of Drosophila larvae: neu-

roanatomy and behaviour" Thesis director: Prof. R.F Stocker

2002 Diploma in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg, Switzerland)

1998 "Maturité fédérale type C" (scientific subsection), in the "Collège de la royale

Abbaye de St. Maurice"

## Languages

French (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (fluent), Spanish (basics).

# Research output

8 research papers (7 first author), 3 reviews, 1 Scienceopen collection, 3 Open source software (2 main author), Meeting Presentations > 25

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520

https://github.com/jcolomb

# Supervision of student

2010-2014 Co-supervisor of the PhD student Christine Damrau (with Dr. B.Brembs) on

the role of octopamine in reward, motivation and motor control in  ${\it Drosophila}.$ 

2008 Co-supervisor of the PhD student Séverine Trannoy (with Dr. G. Isabel and

Dr. N. Gervasi) on the role of dopamine in appetitive learning consolidation in

Drosophila.

2005 Co-supervisor of the diploma work of Claire Huguenin (with Dr. A. Ramaekers)

on the role of NO in olfactory discrimination in *Drosophila* larvae.

# Teaching experience

2016	Animal models of neuropathy, (master student, 2x2h lecture, organisation)
2012 2012 2011	Genetik (bachelor student, 2 x 3 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar) Neurogenetik. (master student, 2 x 2 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar) Practical course neurobiology. (7 x 4 h., Practical course supervision) Entwicklung der Insekten [Insect development] (2 h. lecture)
2011	
2006	Fluorescence and Confocal Microscopy (master student, 3h. lecture)
2003-2006	Studying behavior. (master student, 2 h. lecture)
2003-2005	Developmental- and Neurogenetics (master student, 2 h. lecture).

# Computer skills

Organisation: Outlook, Access, labfolder; Publishing: LATEX, Office, overleaf, markdown, html, figshare; Image processing: Photoshop, Illustrator, Image J; Programming and data analysis: R, Rmarkdown, shiny, Git, Labview; Collaborative working: Github, redmine

### Other tasks

Organisation of the Berlin Open Science meetup:

Part of the march for science Berlin Orga team:

Creation of the T. Preat's and R.F. Stocker's lab website.

Co-director in the theater group "les apostrophes" in 2006

### RESEARCH PRODUCTS

## Open source Software

- (2011-2013) CeTrAn 1.4 to 4.0, developed on Github (https://github.com/jcolomb/CeTrAn). Used for more than three research papers.
- (2016) Viewer data concatenator (shiny app).
- (2013-2016) Collaborating on Rfigshare and Rflybase (https://github.com/ropensci/rfigshare).

## Peer review publications

#### Five most important publications:

- (2016). **Julien Colomb** and Björn Brembs.

  " PKC in motorneurons underlies self-learning, a form of motor learning in Drosophila" PeerJ (e1971).

  cited 3 times
- (2014). **Julien Colomb** and Björn Brembs. "Sub-strains of Drosophila Canton-S differ markedly in their locomotor behavior". F1000RESEARCH (3:176). cited 15 times
- (2009). **Julien Colomb**, Laure Kaiser, Marie-Ange Chabaud, Thomas Preat. "Parametric and genetic analysis of Drosophila appetitive long-term memory and sugar motivation" Genes Brain and Behaviour (8 (4): 407-415). cited 52 times
- (2007). **Julien Colomb**, Nicola Grillenzoni, Ariane Ramaekers, and Reinhard F. Stocker. "Architecture of the primary taste center of *Drosophila melanogaster* larvae". J. comp. neurol. (502: 834-847). cited 72 times
- (2007). **Julien Colomb**, Nicola Grillenzoni, Reinhard F. Stocker, and Ariane Ramaekers. "Complex behavioural changes after odour exposure in *Drosophila* larva". Anim. Behav. (73 (4): 579-85). cited 13 times

#### Other Publications

• (In revision). Christine Damrau, Naoko Toshima, Teiichi Tanimura, Björn Brembs Julien Colomb.

- "Octopamine and Tyramine contribute separately to the counter-regulatory response to sugar deficit in Drosophila." Frontiers
- (2014). Ezequiel Mendoza, **Julien Colomb**, Jürgen Rybak, Hans-Joachim Pflüger, Troy Zars, Constance Scharff, and Björn Brembs.
  - "Drosophila FoxP mutants are deficient in operant self-learning". Plos One (9(6): e100648).
- (2012). **Julien Colomb**, Lutz Reiter, Jedrzej Blaszkiewicz, Jan Wessnitzer and Björn Brembs.
  - "Open Source Tracking and Analysis of Adult *Drosophila* Locomotion in Buridan's Paradigm with and without Visual Targets." Plos One (7(8): e42247).
- (2010). **Julien Colomb**, Björn Brembs "biology of psychology: "simple conditioning"" Communicative and Integrative Biology (3 (2): 142-145).
- $\bullet$  (2008). Julien Colomb
  - "Discriminative learning, learning generalization and masking tests as three strategies to assess olfactory discrimination." Animal Behaviour: New Research 185-192
- (2007). **Julien Colomb**\*, Rüdiger Bader\*, Bettina Pankratz, Anne Schröck, Reinhard F. Stocker, and Michael J. Pankratz.
  - "Genetic dissection of a neural circuit underlying feeding behavior in Drosophila: distinct morphology of single hugin expressing neurons". J. comp. neurol. (502: 848-856).
  - \* the two authors participated equally to this work.
- (2007). **Julien Colomb**, Reinhard F. Stocker "Combined rather than separate pathway for hedonic and sensory aspects of taste in *Drosophila* larvae." FLY (1 (4): 232-234).

# Meeting presentations (4 most representative)

- 2016 Faster and more reproducible science: Open Science. ORAL PRESENTATION at the neurofly meeting, Creta, Greece.
- 2008 New insight into appetitive Long term memory in *Drosophila*. POSTER PRESENTATION at the FENS Forum, Geneva, Switzerland.
- 2006 Sub-regions in the primary taste center of *Drosophila* larvae. ORAL PRESENTATION at the 11th European Drosophila neurobiology Conference, Leuven, Belgium

  Learning by odor exposure in agar plate. ORAL PRESENTATION at the behavioural neurobiology of *Drosophila* larvae meeting, Würzburg, Germany.
- 2002 Functional studies of the chemosensory system of the Drosophila larva using a new tool: the GAL4 / UAS-shi $^{ts}$  system. ORAL PRESENTATION at the Swiss Drosophila meeting, Basel, Switzerland.